Inventory of the Flora Adams Darling Papers 1862-1908
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Flora Adams Darling Papers, 1862-1908
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 D25
4,686 items.
This collection includes correspondence, chiefly 1890-1908 but also dating back as early as 1862, of Flora (Adams) Darling (1840-1910) concerning her founding of the Daughters of the American Revolution, the Daughters of the Revolution, and the U.S. Daughters of 1812.
Edward William Bok,; Flora Adams Darling,; Jessie Benton Frémont,; William Archer Rutherfoord Goodwin,; George Frisbie Hoar,; William Mahone,; John Tyler Morgan,; Alexander Hamilton Stephens,; Lyon Gardiner Tyler.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 4,536 items, 1908.
Acc. No. 1993.59; Gift: ca. 50 items, 1993.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mrs. Darling was born in New Hampshire in 1840, a descendant of Henry Adams who settled in Braintree, Massachusetts, in 1636. She married Col. Edward Irving Darling, 22 years her senior, in 1860, and went with him to live at his Louisiana home. He died of wounds received in battle, December 2, 1863. Her only son was Edward Erving Darling, a minor musician-composer, who died July 13, 1894. Mrs. Darling suffered from repeated attacks of malarial fever and, after 1876, from deafness. Her years of widowhood were spent in writing Mrs. Darling's Letters, or Memoirs of the Civil War A Social Diplomat and other books.
From 1889 to 1896 her major interests and efforts were devoted to the founding of women's patriotic societies. Mrs. Darling's obsession for organizing and ruling patriotic societies, and her willingness to abandon one when her opinion or desires were thwarted, is illustrated by the rapid succession with which the societies followed each other: Daughters of the American Revolution (D.A.R.) founded October 11, 1890; Daughters of the Revolution (D.R.) founded June 18, 1891; Daughters of the United States of the War of 1812, founded January 8, 1892; founded because of disagreement over policies of the D. A. R., policies adopted over the protest of Mrs. Darling. This collection is composed almost entirely of letters written to her during these years of controversy. There are some delightful, pithy and well-written letters in the group.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence, chiefly 1890-1908, of Flora (Adams) Darling, concerning her founding of the Daughters of the American Revolution, the General Society of Daughters of the Revolution, and the National Society, United States Daughters of 1812. Prominent correspondents include Edward William Bok, Jessie Benton Fremont, William Archer Rutherfoord Goodwin, George Frisbie, John Tyler Morgan, William Mahone, Alexander Hamilton Stephens, and Lyon Gardiner Tyler.
Also included is, family correspondence, letters from Spanish Ambassador E. Dupuy deLome, Mrs. Darling's writings, correspondence about her gifts to Bruton Parish Church and the College of William and Mary, newspaper clippings, and miscellany.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 7 series. Series 1 contains letters and information pertaining to the Daughters of the American Revolution; series 2 contains letters and information pertaining to the Daughters of the Revolution; series 3 contains letters and information pertaining to the Daughters of 1812; series 4 contains Official correspondence, bills, and reports; series 5 contains personal letters, series 6 contains miscellaneous items and series 7 contains an addition to the collection, 1993.59.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into series by subject.
Additional Bibliographic and Related Material
Bibliography
Darling, Flora Adams. Founding and organization of the Daughters of the American Revolution and Daughters of the Revolution. Philadelphia: Independence Pub. Co., c1901.
Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Call Number:369.135 D24
Darling, Flora Adams. 1607-1907. Memories of Virginia; a souvenir of founding days. Washington? D.C., c1907.
Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Call Number:F229 .D21
Darling, Flora Adams. Mrs. Darling's letters, or Memories of the civil war. New York: J.W. Lovell company, c1883.
Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Call Number:E605 .D22
Hammond, Jennifer J. Flora Adams Darling and the Daughters of the American Revolution 1993. Honor's Thesis, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Call Number:LD6051 .W5m Hist., 1993, H34
Related Materials
See also letters to Lyon G. Tyler, 1905-1909, concerning the College of William and Mary, historical matters, gifts to the College Library, fundraising writings, portraits of Flora Adams Darling and Jefferson Davis in the President's Office Files, c. 1888-1935, under "Fundraising- Flora Adams Darling." Archives Acc. 1984.19. (27 items)
Index Terms
Persons:
Bok, Edward William, 1863- 1930.; Frémont, Jessie Benton, 1824-1902.; Goodwin, William Archer Rutherfoord, 1869-1939; Hoar, George Frisbie, 1826-1904.; Morgan, John Tyler, 1824-1907.; Mahone, William, 1826-1895.; Stephens, Alexander Hamilton, 1812-1883.; Tyler, Lyon Gardiner, 1853-1935.
Subjects:
General Society of the Daughters of the Revolution.; Daughters of the American Revolution.; National Society, United States Daughters of 1812.; Patriotic societies.
Contents List
  Series 1: Daughters of the American Revolution
- Daughters of the American Revolution, 1890-1905. (Folder 1-15)
  - Letters concerning the D.A.R., 1890. (Folder 1)
    Letter of Mrs. Darling setting forth her views on establishing an organization along the lines of the Daughters of the American Revolution, August 30, 1890. The letter also gives her lineal descent from Andrew Adams of Braintree, Massachusetts.
    October 11, 1890 is the accepted ate of the founding of the Daughters of the American Revolution. This folder contains letters of congratulation from the heads of state societies of the Sons of the American Revolution.
    Letters from early participants in the movement, e.g., Mr. O. McDowell of New York, October 22, 1890; Mrs. Sara A. Pryor (wife of Roger Pryor) of New York, October 20, 1890; Mrs. William D. Cabell of Washington, D. C., November 10, and October 23, 1890; Mrs. Ellen Hardin Walworth of Washington, D. C., November 8, 1890.
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning the founding of a New York chapter of the D. A. R. One letter by Mrs. Darling, January and February 1891. (Folder 2)
  - Letter to Mrs. Darling on D. A. R. matters, March 1891. (Folder 3)
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling, April 1891. (Folder 4)
    A letter from Mrs. Roby of Chicago, April 18, 1891 is most interesting for she was very active at that time in the Grand Army of the Republic.
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling, May and June 1891. (Folder 5)
    A letter of June 10 from Mrs. Roby reveals some of the basis for the internal controversy then raging in the D. A. R.
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling, July thru October 1891. (Folder 6)
    This group of letters reveals the cause of Mrs. Darling's resignation from the D. A. R. and her motives in founding the Daughters of the Revolution.
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling, 1892-1906. (Folder 7)
    See also the fourteen page MSS by Mrs. Darling on the founding of the D. A. R., D. R. and U. S. Daughters of 1812. Also contains a group of letters with threats of legal action relative to the founding of the D. A. R., and a letter from William O. McDowell, a controversial figure in the D. A. R. and the S. A. R., who at one time was asked to resign from the latter organization.
  - Undated letters to Mrs. Darling. (Folder 8)
  - Printed copies of S.A.R. and D.A.R. constitutions. (Folder 9)
    The printed constitution of the S. A. R. with marginal notes by Mrs. Darling. This was used as the basis of the D. A. R. constitution. Also corrected printer's proofs of the first D. A. R. constitution. Two printed copies of the first D. A. R. constitution.
  - Statement by Mrs. Darling setting forth her position in the controversy over the "true history" of the founding of the D. A. R. (Folder 10)
  - Four MSS notebooks of Mrs. Darling's containing notes on the history of the D. A. R. (Folder 11)
  - Two copies of Mrs. Darling's book: The Founding and Organization of the Daughters of the American Revolution (1901). Pamphlet by Mary Desha, Mrs. Darling's anathema, on the founding of the D. A. R., 1901. (Folder 12)
  - Report of the D. A. R. 1890-1897, Washington: Government Printing Office, 1899. (Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1890-1905. (Folder 14)
    Mrs. Darling's financial accounts, the D. A. R., 1890-91; MSS of an address by Mrs. Darling delivered June 17, 1891 at the Tomb of Martyrs, Brooklyn, New York; early D. A. R. application forms, printed bill of the U. S. House of Representatives authorizing the sale of government land to the D. A. R. (site of Continental Hall); and Various newspaper clippings (1891-1905) concerning the D. A. R. and Mrs. Darling.
  - Miscellaneous, 1901-1905. (Folder 15)
    Special D. A. R. edition of The Washington Mirror, April 22, 1905; and issue of Literary Life, March 1901. See also list of New York women invited to a D. A. R. organizational meeting held at Sherry's on February 22, 1901. Also photographs of Mrs. John Risley Putnam (New York), Mary A. Washington (Macon, Ga.), Gertrude Virginian Cortlandt Hamilton (New York), Eliza Thompson Edgerton Newport (Minnesota), and Helen Mason Boynton.
  Series 2: Daughters of the Revolution
- Daughers of the Revolution, 1891-1908. (Folder 16-22)
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning the Daughters of the Revolution, 1891. (Folder 16)
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning the Daughters of the Revolution, 1892-1908 and undated. (Folder 17)
  - Papers relating to the constitution of the Daughters of the Revolution; MSS, pamphlets, circulars and blank applications for membership. (Folder 18)
  - Programs and invitations to special events and social activities of the Daughters of the Revolution, 1891-1908. (Folder 19)
  - Papers, newspaper clippings, and a magazine, 1890-1905. (Folder 20)
    Papers concerning the Daughters of the Revolution, 1896-1907, newspaper clippings, and a copy of Adams' Magazine of General History. The latter contains a brief account of the life of Mrs. Darling.
  - Two printed copies of Mrs. Flora Adams Darling (1891), by C. F. Turner, and Proceedings of the Annual Meeting, General Society, Daughters of the Revolution, 1898 and 1903. (Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous, 1895. (Folder 22)
    Address book listing members of the Daughters of the Revolution (1895). The Prison Ship Martyrs(1895) by Charles E. West, LL. D., a pamphlet on the Americans held prisoner on ships after the British capture of Long Island.
    Printed programs, ballots, circulars, concerning the general Society and the New York State Society of the Daughters of the Revolution.
  Series 3: U.S. Daughters of 1812
- U.S. Daughters of 1812, 1891-1908. (Folder 23-37)
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning the Daughters of 1812, September-December 1891. (Folder 23)
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning the United Daughters of 1812. (The name of this organization varies.), January-March 1892. (Folder 24)
    Letter from Louis J. Allen, an officer aboard the U. S. S. Chicago at Montevideo, Uruguay, mentioning trouble with Chile, February 25, 1892. Letter from Jessie Benton Fremont, February 25, 1892.
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning U. S. Daughters of 1812, April-May 1892. (Folder 25)
    Three interesting letters from Mrs. D. R. Dorris of Nashville, Tenn. On the efforts of the Hermitage Association to save the home of Andrew Jackson. Letter from Mrs. Varina Anne Jefferson Davis at Beauvoir, Mississippi, June 5, 1892.
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning the U. S. Daughters of 1812, June-December 1892. (Folder 26)
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling, 1893-1895. (Folder 27)
    Concerning the U. S. Daughters of 1812, and Broadside of the Key Monument Association of Frederick, Maryland, 1895, soliciting funds to erect a monument at the grave of Francis Scott Key.
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning U. S. Daughters of 1812, 1896. (Folder 28)
    See letter of October 3, 1896, from Dayton, Ohio, mentioning rumors of Mrs. Darling's plans to retire and live at Old Point Comfort, Virginia.
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning the U. S. Daughters of 1812, 1897-1908. (Folder 29)
    Circular letter of the American Institute of Civics regarding a national celebration honoring the surviving generals and admirals of the Civil War. The program was cancelled, April 13, 1898, because of threat of war.
    Letter from Mrs. Eliza W. Hall, January 25, 1901, indicating Mrs. Darling was to receive a percent of the annual receipts of the U. S. Daughters of 1812. Copy of a letter from Mrs. Darling to Mrs. Slade, December 10, 1902. The letter well reveals Mrs. Darling's domineering character, and also refers to the successful conclusion of her 30 year suit against the government for the loss of jewelry and property in New Orleans during the Civil War.
    Letter regarding an oil portrait of Mrs. Darling being placed in the Detroit Museum of Art until a suitable place in the U. S. Daughters of 1812 could be build, November 16, 1904. Letter to Mrs. Darling from Mrs. Lillie B. Titus, July 13, 1905, explaining the Massachusetts chapter of the U. S. Daughters of 1812 withdrawal from the National Society. This is followed by a 20 page MSS on the same subject. Letter from Mrs. Nannie Pugh Richardson, of New Orleans, offering to sell Julio's painting of the last meeting of Lee and Jackson, March 6, 1907.
  - Undated letters to Mrs. Darling concerning the U.S. Daughters of 1812. (Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous. (Folder 31)
    Three rough drafts of a certificate of incorporation for the U. S. Daughters of 1812. Papers relating to the constitution of the general and state societies of the U. S. Daughters of 1812. See also the following pamphlets: U. S. Daughters of 1812, New York State Chapter, Constitution and Bylaws(three copies); U. S. Daughters of 1812, Massachusetts State Chapter, Constitution and Bylaws(two copies); Constitution of U. S. Daughters of 1812, National Society(three copies); Constitution and Bylaws, U. S. Daughters of 1812, Illinois State Society; Constitution and Bylaws of the U. S. Daughters of 1812, Pennsylvania State Society. List of officers, managers, and alternates of the Board of Lady Managers, World's Columbian Exposition. Membership forms, invitations, etc. Of state and national U. S. Daughters of 1812 societies. Printed constitutions and bylaws: National Society, U. S. Daughters of 1812(three copies); U. S. Daughters of 1812 of Illinois; and U. S. Daughters of 1812 of Pennsylvania. Invitations to state U. S. Daughters of 1812 programs and social events.
  - Papers relating to the U. S. Daughters of 1812 (continued). (Folder 32)
    Petitions and resolutions on varied matters from U. S. Daughters of 1812 organizational problems to Mrs. Darling's request for franking privilege. Official Register of Officers and Honorary Members of the General Society and Historic Council of the 1776 U. S. Daughters of 1812. All entries in this notebook are in Mrs. Darling's hand.
    Notebook containing copies of legal letters relative to the controversy over the incorporation of the U. S. Daughters of 1812.
  - Scrapbook of mementos and notes of the U. S. Daughters of 1812 and other organizations to which Mrs. Darling belonged; also some addresses delivered by her. (Folder 33 and 34)
  - Miscellaneous, 1904-1908. (Folder 35)
    Printed pieces: Mrs. Darling's A Plea in the Interest of Harmony; Programme for Bronze Statue of Major General Alexander Macomb(includes biographical sketch and three photographs of Macomb); pamphlet by Mrs. Edward Roby explaining her part in the U. S. Daughters of 1812 controversy, 1905-1908. Mrs. Darling's annual address of January 8, 1904 for the National Society of the U. S. Daughters of 1812. Notices of meetings, programmes, and circular letters.
  - Clippings concerning the U. S. Daughters of 1812. (Folder 36)
  - Undated letters to Mrs. Darling concerning various patriotic societies. (Folder 37)
  Series 4: Official Letters, Bills, and Reports
- Official Letters, Bills, and Reports, 1864-1907. (Folder 38-42)
  - Letters to Mrs. Darling concerning her claim against the U. S. government for jewelry and money lost in New Orleans in 1863 while traveling under a flag of truce, 1874-1907. (Folder 38)
    Letters from Fernando Wood. Letter from U. S. Senator George F. Hoar, July 19, 1888, summarizing the legal points involved in Mrs. Darling's case against the government. Letter from General J. M. Schofield, St. Augustine, Florida, February 6, 1900. Letter of Mrs. Darling, April 22, 1897, intimating that pressure by her enemies in several patriotic societies has caused unfavorable consideration of her claim before Congress.
  - Printed material concerning Mrs. Darling's claim against the U.S. government, 1864-1904. (Folder 39)
    Printed bills and reports concerning Mrs. Darling's claim, which began in 1864 after a personal visit to President Lincoln and was finally settled by an Act of Congress in November 1904. Newspaper clippings concerning the claim. Newspaper clippings of 1883 concerning the demand for Confederate bonds in the London market and Judah P. Benjamin's part in promoting their sale.
  - Mrs. Darling's correspondence, 1897-1898. (Folder 40)
    Concerning the approaching War with Spain. Letters of Sept 10, 1897 and November 23, 1897 from the Spanish Ambassador E. Dupuy DeLome concerning yellow journalism and anti-Spanish feeling in the U. S.
    Letters from Mrs. Darling's nephew who ran away from home to join Roosevelt and "The Rough Riders," January to August 1898. The nephew, Gordon Everett, died of the effects of his army service before he was 18 years old.
    Letter to the president attacking conditions in the U. S. Army, August 28, 1898. Letter from Sergeant G. H. Bates, August 31, 1898, enclosing newspaper clippings and criticizing the army. Letter from an "army deserter" of September 2, 1898. Letter, Christmas 1898, from Mrs. Darling to Ambassador DeLome.
  - Mrs. Darling's correspondence concerning The Crucifixion, a painting by George B. Matthews, which she presented to St. Peter's Catholic Church in Mount Clemens, Michigan in memory of her son, Edward. (Folder 41)
  - Letters,lists, and a statement, 1907. (Folder 42)
    Letter of November 26, 1907 from Mrs. Darling offering her papers to the College. Typed list of books and relics given to the William and Mary Library in 1907. A statement by Mrs. Darling establishing the collection and setting forth its purposes and dedications. Letters from W. A. R. Goodwin to Mrs. Darling, February 27, 1907, relative to the Daughters of Founders and Patriots of America giving the chair for the governor's seat in Bruton Parish Church in memory of Governor Matthews.
    Also correspondence between Mrs. Darling and Lyon G. Tyler and others, 27 items.
  Series 5: Personal Letters
- Personal Letters, 1884-1909. (Folder 43-53)
  - Personal letters to Mrs. Darling, 1862-1883. (Folder 43)
    Three letters from Fernando Wood, 1862-1864, relating to Mrs. Darling's pass to the South and her return. Series of letters to Mrs. Darling from Senator John T. Morgan of Alabama, 1881 - some seem like love letters! Letter of Alexander H. Stephens to Mrs. Darling, August 2, 1882.
  - Personal letters, 1884. (Folder 44)
    Primarily concerning Mrs. Darling's book of Civil War letters. Letters of Jefferson Davis, January 19 and May 7, 1884 (in Jefferson Davis Papers). Letter from S. W. Cunningham of N. Y., publisher of Our Day, an "exponent of Southern Sentiment," June 6, 1884. The author remarks, "I became a rebel on the day of my surrender at Fort Donelson - and you judge Andrew John correctly." Letter from Francis C. Lawson, editor of The Negro American, reviewing the difficulties of his work before the appearance of his first issue, July 12, 1884. Letter of Senator John T. Morgan, July 13, 1884, on the strong Democratic Party platform and the approaching election. Letter from Harrison Phoebus, proprietor of the Hygeia Hotel at Old Point Comfort, Virginia, August 15, 1884.
  - Personal letters to Mrs. Darling, 1884-1889. (Folder 45)
    Letter of Jefferson Davis, (in Jefferson Davis Papers), January 24, 1884. Letter of George M. Guild, May 14, 1885 mentioning Mrs. Darling's calls on President Cleveland. Letter from Mark M. Pomeroy of The U. S. Democrat, Washington, D. C., July 15, 1885, referring to Mrs. Darling's interest in raising funds to erect a monument to Mrs. Surratt. Letter from Horatio King, November 14, 1885. Letter from General William Mahone of Petersburg, Virginia. See also several 1885 and 1886 letters from Edward W. Bok.
  - Personal letters to Mrs. Darling, 1890-1892. (Folder 46)
  - Personal letters to Mrs. Darling, 1893-1899. (Folder 47)
  - Personal letters to Mrs. Darling, 1900-1903. (Folder 48)
  - Personal letters to Mrs. Darling, 1904-1906. (Folder 49)
    Letters in Folders 46 through 49 are entirely personal in nature and contain no mention of political events.
  - Personal correspondence, 1906-1909. (Folder 50-53)
  Series 6: Miscellaneous and Bound Volumes
- Miscellaneous and Bound Volumes. (Folder 54-67)
  - Incomplete letters and fragments. (Folder 54)
  - Invoices, receipts, and invitations to social functions. (Folder 55)
  - Papers relating to Adams' Magazine, Columbia Daughters, Crown Society of America, Founders of America, Founders' Kin Alliance, and Columbian Art Alliance International. (Folder 56)
  - Papers relating to the American Flag House and the Betsy Ross Memorial Association in which Mrs. Darling's brother, John Quincy Adams, was a leading figure. (Folder 56A)
  - Papers relating to the sons of the American Revolution and the Sons of the Revolution. (Folder 57)
  - Papers relating to the Edward Irving Darling Musical Society (in memory of Mrs. Darling's only child who died February 13, 1894), the Lamperti School of Music, and a proposed school for Indian girls. (Folder 58)
  - Miscellaneous cards and fragments. (Folder 59)
  - Writings of Flora A. Darling. (Folder 60 and 61)
    Including printed copies of Memories of Virginia, A War Episode, a manuscript copy of Two Virginians, Explorers to the Pacific Ocean, 1803-1806, three memorandum books, and several poems and articles in manuscript.
  - Writings of Francis A. Adams. (Folder 62)
    Including a printed copy of Who Rules America?(1899).
  - Printed ephemerals chiefly relating to patriotic societies. (Folder 63)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets chiefly relating to patriotic societies. (Folder 64 and 65)
  - Photographs and engravings. (Folder 66)
  - Letterheads, envelopes, labels. (Folder 67)
  - Scrapbooks of Flora A. Darling., 58 pages. 13 3/4 by 11 inches. (Folder 68)
    Scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings and other data on the history of the Daughters of the American Revolution, Daughters of the Revolution, and the United States Daughters of 1812.
  - Scrapbook of Flora A. Darling., 156 pages. 13 3/4 by 9 inches. (Folder 68)
    Scrapbook containing newspaper clippings chiefly devoted to the controversy relative to the founding of the Daughters of the American Revolution. Some of the articles were written by Mrs. Darling under the pseudonym Mignon.
  - Biographical sketch of Gen. Charles W. Darling. New York, Atlas Publishing and Engraving Co., 1890. (Folder 68)
- Addition to Collection, 1993.59, 1883-1902, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  - Genealogical material. (Box-folder 1:1-13)